Inventory of the W. H. (William Harold) Hutt Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Correspondence (Box 67)
  - Miscellany. Institute for Law and Policy Analysis, 1975-1983. (Box 67)
    Includes letters to others
- Article by Sylvester Petro on labor disputes, undated
- Correspondence (Box 68)
  - General
    - Ro-Rz, 1965-1982 (Folder 68: 1)
    - Sa-Si, 1969-1983 (Folder 68: 2)
    - Sk-Sz, 1968-1983 (Folder 68: 3)
    - S-V, 1958-1980 (Folder 68: 4)
    - T, 1971-1981 (Folder 68: 5)
  - Seldon, Arthur, 1969-1982 (Folder 68: 6)
  - Shenfield, Arthur, 1969-1979 (Folder 68: 7)
  - Shenoy, Sudha, 1972-1974 (Folder 68: 8)
  - Standard Bank of South Africa, 1978-1982 (Folder 68: 9)
  - Syfrets Trust, 1969-1982 (Folder 68: 10)
  - Templeton, K. S., 1972-1977 (Folder 68: 11)
- Tempo, 1981-1983 (Folder 68: 12)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1962-1983. (Box 68)
  Includes letters to Ronald Reagan and Henry Regnery, memoranda, and a statement about energy policy
- Correspondence (Box 69)
  - General
    - U, 1962-1982 (Folder 69: 1)
    - V, 1967-1978 (Folder 69: 2)
    - W-Z, 1964-1967 (Folder 69: 3)
  - Musical Heritage Society, 1988 (Folder 69: 4)
  - Miscellany, 1965-1985 (Folder 69: 5)
- Articles by William Hutt
  - "The Aggregate Demand Fallacy,", undated (Folder 69: 6)
  - "The Factory System of the 19th Century," 1926 March; "Significance of State Interference with Interest Rates," 1933 September; "War Demand, Entrepreneurship and the Distributive Problem," 1941 November; and "The Sanctions for Privacy under Private Enterprise,", 1942 August (Folder 69: 7)
  - "Further Aspects of Russian Statistics," 1945 December; "Full Employment and the Future of Industry," 1945 September (review article); and "South Africa's Salvation in Classic Liberalism,", 1965 (Folder 69: 8)
- Miscellany, 1976-1985. (Box 69)
  Includes draft letters, letters to the editors, and refutation by William Hutt of Carl Rowan's comments on apartheid; "Should America Adopt an Industrial Policy?" article by William H. Peterson and Lester Thurow; "The Libertarian Legitimacy of the State: A Critical Interpretation of Robert Nozick's Anarchy, State, and Utopia, working paper, James M. Buchanan; and "The Annual Guide to Public Policy Experts"
- "Cape Colonial Finance," chapter IV, "A Monetary History of South Africa," by William Hutt [?], undated (Box-folder 70: 1)
- "W. H. Hutt's Contributions in Economics, Politics, and Philosophy" conference, Dallas, Texas, 1987 September 18-20. (Folder 70: 2)
  Includes list of organizers, authors, and participants, and summary of the conference
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1987-1988 (Folder 70: 3-4)
- Agreement between William Hutt and the Department of Economics, University of Dallas, Irving, Texas, regarding publication of the Strike-Threat System and with the Liberty Fund for the publication of Theory of Idle Resources, 1972-1985. (Folder 70: 5)
- "Autobiography of an Economist," William Hutt, undated. (Folder 70: 6)
- Correspondence, A-C, 1983-1987. (Folder 70: 7)
  Includes article, comments on William Hutt's draft autobiography, curriculum vitae, and list of his selected contributions
- Miscellany, 1970-1983. (Folder 70: 8)
  Articles, biographical information about Friedrich Hayek and others, drafts of writings by William Hutt relating to labor unions, notes, and reviews
- "The Impoverishers--A Postscript,", 1984 (Folder 70: 9-12)
- Interview of William Hutt by Morgan O. Reynolds, Irving, Texas, 1984 May 17. (Box 70)
  Edited transcript and a letter
- Miscellany, 1936-1985.
  Includes articles by William Hutt and others relating to apartheid, Keynesianism, and South African economy; book reviews; conference report on "Austrian Economics;" drafts of "The Impoverishers" and "Politically Impossible;" interview of William Hutt; index to articles and papers by William Hutt; journal; letters; newsletters; notes; royalty reports; and summary report on "The Role of Business in Society"
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 71)
  - Collection of articles--Academic affairs, 1971-1982 and undated. (Folder 71: 1)
    Includes "How to End Inflation and Abnormal Unemployment," "Distributive Justice and Colour Antagonism," "The Fiasco of Keynesian Policy," and "Coordination and the Price System: An Examination of the Multiplier and Acceleration Fallacies." Also includes review of William Hutt's "Wages Flow" economic theory, 1971, letter to the editor on "Reagan's Courage," 1982, and list of Hutt's publications, undated
  - "The Sanctions for Managerial Command,", undated (Folder 71: 2)
  - "The Non-Market Determination of Contractual Incomes,", undated (Folder 71: 3)
  - Drafts of William Hutt's writings relating to managerial exploitation, role of labor unions, and related issues, 1964-1965 and undated. (Folder 71: 4)
    Includes letters to him
  - "Keynes and the Speculator,", undated (Folder 71: 5)
  - "The Effect of Trade Union on Distribution,", 1968 and undated. (Folder 71: 6)
    Includes clippings, notes, and statement
  - "The Multiplier,", undated (Folder 71: 7)
  - Drafts of William Hutt's writings relating to gold exchange, inflation, wages, and related issues, undated (Folder 71: 8)
  - Discarded materials, undated (Folder 71: 9)
  - Draft chapters from A Rehabilitation of Say's Law, 1975 and undated (Folder 71: 10)
  - "The Gold Standard and Orthodox Thought,", undated (Folder 71: 11)
  - Writings in Austrian Economists, 1973 and undated. (Folder 71: 12)
    Includes reviews [?], article, clippings, and notes
  - "Valueless Resources,", undated (Folder 71: 13)
  - "Keynes,", 1937-1941 and undated. (Folder 71: 14)
    Includes articles by F. H. Knight
  - Reviews by F. S. Brooman and others of William Hutt's books, 1957-1964. (Folder 71: 15)
    Includes clippings, letters, and memoranda
- Idle Resources by William Hutt, 1974-1976 and undated. (Box 71)
  Includes record of correspondence
- Drafts of William Hutt's writings relating to labor relations, wage issue, and other related matters, undated
- "Capitalism and the Historians," article by R. M. Hartwell, undated
- Miscellany, 1961-1986. (Box-folder 72: 1)
  Includes articles relating to budget, gold standard, income distribution, inflation, and labor relations, 1961-1981; issues of the Congressional Record documenting the proceedings and debates of the 97th Congress, 1981; newsletters relating to energy issues, free-market economics, inequality, and libertarian principles, 1978-1980; and reports on welfare system and health issues, 1985-1986
- Miscellany, 1927-1988. (Box 72)
  Includes articles by others, clipping, reports, and newsletters relating to balanced budget, competition and monopoly, Keynesian economics, inflation, liberty and prosperity, national health insurance, situation in South Africa and Latin America, reports, supply side economics, welfare state, and related economic issues. Also includes microfiche of an article by E. L. Godkin and a bibliography
- William Hutt's writings and lecture notes (Box 73)
  - Lecture notes on Alfred Marshall [?], undated (Folder 73: 1)
  - "Hutcheson and Adam Smith,", undated (Folder 73: 2)
  - Corrected notes on mercantilism [?], undated (Folder 73: 3)
  - Monetary theory and monetary economics, undated. (Folder 73: 4-13)
    Contains lecture notes for an economics class and articles from the Wall Street Journal
  - "Keynesian Bias in the Use of the Phillip's Curve,", undated (Folder 73: 14)
  - "Latent Inflation,", undated (Folder 73: 15)
  - Notes on Heyne, undated (Folder 73: 16)
  - "Choice in Currency: A Way to Stop Inflation,", 1976 (Folder 73: 17)
- Writings of William Hutt in South African Journal of Economics (Box 73)
  - "Economic Aspects of the Report of the Poor White Commission,", 1933 September
  - "Economic Method and the Concept of Competition,", 1934 March
  - "Natural and Contrived Scarcities,", 1935 September
  - "The Price Mechanism and Economic Immobility,", 1936 September
  - "Economic Aspects of the Report of the Cape Coloured Commission,", 1938 June
  - "Notes and Memoranda: The Development of the Soviet Economic System,", 1946 September
  - "The Notion of Money of Constant Value,", 1953 September and December
  - "New Light of Wicksell,", 1959 March
  - Rejoinder to Professor Milton Friedman by William Hutt, undated
  - Notes on some fundamental concepts for lectures on a class in economics, undated
  - "A Critique of the National Labor Policy: Proposals for Legal and Constitutional Research," by William Hutt [?], undated
  - "Toespraak Door," Milton Friedman, Mont Pelerin Society special European meeting, Amsterdam, the Netherlands, 1977 April 15
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 74)
  - "Money and Employment,", undated (Folder 74: 1)
  - "The Relation between M'd and M'c,", undated. (Folder 74: 2)
    Notes for economics class
  - "The Nature of Liquidity Preference"--Keynes' economics, undated (Folder 74: 3-4)
  - "The Consumption Fallacy,", undated (Folder 74: 5)
  - "The Aggregate Demand Fallacy,", undated (Folder 74: 6)
  - "Implications of the No-Strike System,", undated (Folder 74: 7)
  - "Monetary Theory,", undated (Folder 74: 8)
  - "Definitions,", undated (Folder 74: 9)
  - "The Expenditure Fallacy,", undated (Folder 74: 10)
  - Fragments of writings about labor relations, undated (Folder 74: 11)
  - Article on gold standard, undated (Folder 74: 12)
  - J. B. Say--Introduction, undated (Folder 74: 13)
  - "Say's Law,", undated (Folder 74: 14)
  - Idle Resources, undated. (Folder 74: 15)
    Typescript and holograph
- "Can You Fool All of the People All of the Time?" Gordon Tullock (Folder 74: 16)
- Miscellany, 1970. (Folder 74: 17)
  Includes articles by others relating to education, inflation, role of the entrepreneur, and trade union; letter; notes; report on business opportunities in South Africa; schedule of Mont Pelerin Society meeting
- Material, 1976-1977. (Box 74)
  Includes articles by others about banking and denationalization of money and Jesse Helms' speech on monetary research and education in the Congressional Record
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 75)
  - Say's Law--"The Position of the Prevailing Orthodoxy of the 1920's and 1930's,", undated (Folder 75: 1)
  - "Monetary Economics,", undated. (Folder 75: 2-4)
  - "The Propensity to Consume and the Multiplier Fallacy,", undated (Folder 75: 5-6)
  - "Unanimity Versus Non-Discrimination (As Criteria for Constitutional Validity),", undated (Folder 75: 7)
  - "The Relation between Mc and Md,", undated (Folder 75: 8)
  - "Walras,", undated (Folder 75: 9)
  - Drafts about W. S. Jevons and Alfred Marshall, undated (Folder 75: 10)
  - Comments on Heyne's The Economic Way of Thinking, undated (Folder 75: 11-14)
  - "Definitions,", undated (Folder 75: 15-16)
  - "The Expenditure Fallacy,", undated (Folder 75: 17-18)
  - "The Unemployment Equilibrium Fallacy,", undated (Folder 75: 19)
  - "Savings and Investment,", undated (Folder 75: 20)
  - International credit system, undated (Folder 75: 21)
  - "Consumption Fallacy,", undated (Folder 75: 22-23)
  - "Notes on Alchian and Allen,", undated (Folder 75: 24)
  - "Notes on Alchian and Allen,", undated (Box-folder 76: 1-3)
  - "Fundamentals of Economics,", undated (Folder 76: 4-8)
  - "Unanimity versus Non-Discrimination (As Criteria for Constitutional Validity),", undated (Folder 76: 9)
  - "Economic Power and Labor Unions,", undated. (Folder 76: 10)
    Abstract, foreword, and summary
  - "Delegation of Authority and Responsibility,", undated (Folder 76: 11)
  - "Walras,", undated (Folder 76: 12)
  - "Bentham, Say, J. S. Mill, and Senior,", undated (Folder 76: 13-14)
  - J. S. Mill on "Liberty,", undated (Folder 76: 15)
  - "Keynesian System,", undated (Folder 76: 16)
  - History of economic thought
    - Lectures, undated (Folder 76: 17)
    - "The Roman Philosophers,", undated. (Folder 76: 18-19)
      Lecture notes
    - "Mercantilism,", undated. (Folder 76: 20)
- Student paper on "Monetary Theory,", 1977 May 10 (Box 76)
- "Adam Smith, Adam Ferguson, and the Division of Labor," William Hutt, undated (Box-folder 77: 1)
- "Locke in the Context of the American Revolution: Notes towards a Theory of Ideology," Richard Ashcraft, 1976 November (Folder 77: 2)
- Writings by William Hutt, undated. (Box 77)
- Student papers on labor economics and history of economic thought, 1976
- Article by Wilhelm A. Kewenig, undated
- Miscellany, 1971-1987. (Box 78)
  Includes articles by others, bulletin, economic report, letters, and press release relating to expenditure, dollar overvaluation, education, foreign aid, Keynesian theory, labor relations, libertarian principles, market values, productivity, role of women in business, trade union, unemployment, and other related issues
- Miscellaneous journals and other publications, 1958-1987
- Correspondence with William M. H. Hammett and others, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 79: 1)
- Copies of biographies, undated (Folder 79: 2)
- Report on the Second International University of the Open Society, undated (Folder 79: 3)
- Letters of current interest, 1982 (Folder 79: 4)
- Writings by William Hutt
  - W. S. Jevons, undated. (Folder 79: 5-6)
  - Walras, undated (Folder 79: 7)
  - "Accidental Fallacy,", undated (Folder 79: 8)
  - "Africa's Defiant White Tribe,", 1977 July 27. (Folder 79: 9)
    Television program
  - Alfred Marshall, undated. (Folder 79: 10)
- "Worker Alienation and the Structure of the Firm,", undated. (Folder 79: 11)
  Article by Eirik G. Furubotn
- "John Locke as Economist and Social Scientist," Karen I. Vaughn, symposium, 1976 November 18-21 (Folder 79: 12)
- Article by Patrick Kelly on John Locke's Two Treatises of Government, undated (Folder 79: 13)
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 79)
  - "The Free Choice of Gold as Currency,", undated
  - "The Strike-Threat,", undated
  - "Objections to the Thesis - Preliminary Discussion,", undated
  - "The Nature of the Strike,", undated
  - "The Bargaining Power Concept" "Exploitation--The Shut-In and the Shut-Out,", undated
  - "The Standard Rate,", undated
  - "Labor's Share,", undated
  - "Tocqueville's Message for South Africa,", 1964
  - "Russia's Advantage over Capitalist Nations,", 1957
  - "Conditions for Economic Growth-II--Inflationary Policy Must Be Renounced,", 1964
- Biographical information about William Hutt and reports, 1982-1983, and clippings, 1927-1948
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 80)
  - "The Face and the Mask of Unionism,", undated (Folder 80: 1)
  - "The Free Market" as a criterion for the "Just Price,", undated (Folder 80: 2)
  - "South Africa and Apartheid,", undated (Folder 80: 3)
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship,", undated. (Folder 80: 4)
- "Wage Regulation under the Statute of Artificers," R. Keith Kelsall, undated (Folder 80: 5)
- Richard E. Wagner, undated. (Folder 80: 6)
  Foreword by William Hutt
- "The Origins of Keynesian Mythology: Britain between the Wars," Brian Kantor, 1979 February 22 (Folder 80: 7)
- Articles by Milton Friedman and others about labor, undated (Folder 80: 8)
- Address by Roger Freeman, 1970 (Box 80)
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 81)
  - "Locke's Theory of Mutual Rights: Reinterpretation and Reclamation," J. Charles King, undated (Folder 81: 1)
  - "Credo,", undated (Folder 81: 2)
  - "Equality and Iniquity: In the Determination of Incomes and Taxes,", undated. (Folder 81: 3-4)
  - List of selected contributions by William Hutt, undated. (Folder 81: 5)
    Includes some writings
  - "The Yugoslavian System,", undated (Folder 81: 6-7)
  - Drafts relating to business practices and consumers' interests, undated (Folder 81: 8)
  - "Keynes," chapter II, undated (Folder 81: 9)
  - "Labor's Disadvantage in Bargaining,", undated (Folder 81: 10-11)
  - "Some Basic Explanations,", undated (Folder 81: 12)
  - "Human Attributes: Envy and Acquisitiveness,", undated (Folder 81: 13)
  - "Bargaining,", undated (Folder 81: 14)
  - "Non-Market Influences on Incomes: Social Effects,", undated (Folder 81: 15)
- "The Constancy of Locke's Individualism," Eric Mack, undated (Folder 81: 16)
- "Locke on Property and Consent," David Kelley, undated (Folder 81: 17)
- "John Locke: His Harmony between Liberty and Virtue," Donald J. Devine, undated (Folder 81: 18)
- Article, "Of the Production of Security" by Gustav de Molinari, undated (Box 81)
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 82)
  - "Bargaining,", undated. (Folder 82: 1)
    Typescript
  - "Non-Market Influences on Incomes: Social Effects,", undated (Folder 82: 2)
  - "Contractual Incomes under Market Determination,", undated (Folder 82: 3-4)
  - "Are Labor Unions Privileged Aristocracies?", undated (Folder 82: 5-6)
  - "The Neglected Victims,", undated (Folder 82: 7-8)
  - "Economizing Displacement,", undated (Folder 82: 9-10)
  - "The Sanctions for Managerial Command,", undated (Folder 82: 11-12)
  - "Democracy and Consumers' Sovereignty,", undated (Folder 82: 13-14)
  - "The Principle of Social Justice,", undated (Folder 82: 15-16)
- "The Function of Losses and Profits,", undated (Folder 82: 17-18)
- "Productivity and Wage Rates,", undated (Folder 82: 19)
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship,", undated (Folder 82: 20)
  - "Codetermination,", undated (Folder 82: 21)
  - "The Yugoslavian System,", undated (Folder 82: 22)
  - "The Justice of Market-Determined Wage-Rates and the Mythic Character of Labor's Disadvantage,", undated (Folder 82: 23)
  - "Productivity and Wage Rates,", undated (Box-folder 83: 1)
  - "Shared Entrepreneurship,", undated (Folder 83: 2)
  - "Codetermination,", undated (Folder 83: 3)
  - "The Yugoslavian System,", undated (Folder 83: 4)
  - "The Justice of Market-Determined Wage-Rates and the Mythic Character of Labor's Disadvantage,", undated (Folder 83: 5)
- William Hutt, undated. (Folder 83: 6)
  Includes his biographical sketch, list of selected contributions, and the drafts of his writings: "Definitions," "Equality and Equity," "Society's Problems Under Economic Freedom," "Credo," "The Free Market as Providing a Criterion for the Just Price," "Shared Entrepreneurship," "Proportional Voting," "Prospects for Reform," "The Special Case of the Republic of South Africa," and untitled drafts
  - Corrections, undated (Folder 83: 7)
  - "Equality and Equity: In the Determination of Incomes and Taxes,", undated. (Folder 83: 8-9)
    Includes retyped pages and clippings
- Miscellany, 1932-1977. (Folder 83: 10)
  Includes articles by others; "Analyzing the Brown Report on the Princeton Faculty and Liberal Imbalance," newsletter from the University Professors for Academic Order, Inc., 1974 October; "Workshop Series on Unions and Higher Education," proposal submitted to National Advisory Council on Business and Higher Education, 1974 October; "Africa's Defiant White Tribe," television program scripts, 1977; and a report on national labor policy, undated
- Pamphlet--Under Siege: The Story of the Assault on Academic Freedom, undated (Box 83)
- Writings by William Hutt (Box 84)
  - "Equality and Equity in the Determination of Incomes and Taxes,", undated. (Folder 84: 1-2)
    Includes preface
  - "Progressive Taxation as a Cause of Inequality,", undated (Folder 84: 3)
  - "Proportional Voting,", undated (Folder 84: 4)
  - "Society's Problems under Economic Freedom,", undated (Folder 84: 5)
  - "Credo,", undated (Folder 84: 6)
- Article, brochures, and speech by others, 1935-1976, and undated, relating to apartheid, economy in Chile and China, health insurance, Keynes' theory and its consequences, labor unions and bargaining, political issues affecting South Africa, social security, and tax reform. (Folder 84: 7-8)
  Includes a guide for political aspirants
- Articles by William Hut--Discriminating Monopoly and the Consumer" and "Civil Rights and Young Conservatives," Modern Age, 1966 and undated (Box 84)
- Catalog de La Coleccion Hutt in memoriam of William Hutt, Universidad Francisco Marroquin, undated; Economic Journal, 1936 March; and Turnover, 1973 April
- William Hutt--Address, articles, drafts of chapters of his books, and lecture notes (Box 85)
  - "Roman and Medieval Philosophers"--History of economic thought class, undated (Folder 85: 1)
  - "Walras,", undated (Folder 85: 2)
  - "W. S. Jevons,", undated (Folder 85: 3)
  - "Stability or Strikes," article, undated; "Inflation and the Unions," address, 1972 March 14; "Fragile Constitutions (A reply to Thomas Molnar)" undated; "A Rejoinder to Professor Milton Friedman," undated; "Seeds of Change in South Africa," article, undated; biographical notes, undated; list of selected contributions, undated; opinions of others about his writings, undated; "Distributive Justice and Colour Antagonism," 1943; and "The Financial Position of the Union of South Africa,", 1949 January 19 (Folder 85: 4)
- Examination, undated; student papers, 1977 (Box 85)
- South African Journal of Economics, 1935-1964
- Press release about an African exhibition opening at the University of Dallas, 1974 September 22